goes about understanding how employment
happens uh which is a fancy way of
saying how to get a job and how people
are given jobs how they find jobs and
stuff like that and I I'm going to try
to net it out for you as fast as
possible um elements of this video are
included in other videos but oh well uh
the number one thing to take away from
this video is to understand that getting
a job is about trust it's about trust
I've talked about this a lot
trust is what gets you the job that
means to get a job you need to convince
somebody to trust you enough to pay
you that's it that's it and I know that
sounds really simple and everything
every other thing related to getting a
job comes back to that one thing and
this is so important that people
understand it before they understand
anything else should I use LinkedIn
should I go to this conference blah all
of those other decisions are based on
this one
decision is what I'm about to do going
to
promote people's ability to have trust
in me to do this job that's it and it's
so important that you understand that
employment is about trust um that and
and so there's a couple of secondary
things you can kind of infer from this
number one anything that you do that
detracts from your thank you for that
any anything you do that detracts from
your ability to be
trustworthy uh is going to hinder your
ability to have a job uh I I I I love
Firefly and there's a it's all about
reputation your reputation with me
Malcolm Reynolds is solid is solid is
real my wife loves to talk about this
all the time too reputation is a fancy
way of saying you can be trusted to do
whatever it is that you say you're going
to do and that is sort of a part of the
of the employment equation um you
everybody along the way is going to have
to be
convinced that you can be trusted to do
what it is you think and that includes
you starting with you you have got to
convince yourself and there's other
videos about you know mental frame of
mind and mental preparation to get
started on a career path but you've got
to trust yourself to do the job that
means you know I know I know he can get
the job but can't he do the job I'm not
arguing that with you I'm not arguing
with that with you if you know that
movie reference you're
awesome I know he can get the job but
can't he do the job so it's all about
trust and it's not just the person who's
going to get you the job it's the person
who's going to get you the interview
with their manager who's going to say
and I quote You' being an idiot to not
hire this
guy that's how employment happens it's
not just getting the person who's going
to pay you to trust you it is but
secondarily it's getting all the people
you know in your Camp to also trust you
and that begins with you and then and
then beyond you it's the person next to
you it's the person at your meet up it's
your best friend it's your it's your
spouse they got to trust you they're
trusting you to make them money and keep
them healthy and stuff in some cases not
all but you know so you got to get
people to trust you and the way you get
them to trust you is to become authentic
and to produce Act ual value and for
yourself proof for yourself so so that
that's that's the next part of this how
employment happens in order to get
people to trust you you know you can be
the you could be the most trustworthy
person and and have the most skills of
all unless you can prove it and I have a
story about this so one of the guys that
I helped uh to Mentor he ended up in
Columbia he's he he uh he's
um um he's obsessed with AI obsessed
with it he he I mean he was brilliant he
brilliant he taught himself all the
stuff to do his own AI models he would
come in and and we would have mentoring
sessions together and and I had no idea
where he was coming from he was like
writing his own real net programs and
all kinds of stuff I mean the guy was a
genius I mean he was a genius his brain
was so sharp um he had a little bit of a
hygiene problem I had to Once tell him
you know you need to have a shower
before you come here and you know says
the bike Packer guy right
um but he was just so brilliant but you
know what when it came time for him and
employment employment is in this case
it's not employment but it's the same
idea so he had to get to go to college
so it came time for him to go to college
you know he had extremely rich parents
his his his mother was a vice president
and executive on a on a very on a board
at a very high high-end tech company
which I will not name um you know and
their family had all gone to Columbia or
you know Ivy League schools and stuff
like that and and he was getting ready
to go to college with all this great
knowledge I mean this guy this kid go
anybody would be so lucky to have them
in their college or to have him uh work
for them right and I knew this and I
wanted to be able to say this and so it
came time to give you know to help them
out help them go to school and I I was
always in kind of a dilemma I was like
do I write a Rec letter of
recommendation you know and people would
ask me all the time can you write me a
really great letter recommendation and I
always felt kind of dir about doing that
because I was also getting paid they
were paying me to Mentor them and then
they were also you know having me write
in a letter recommendation it was almost
like they were paying me or have them
you know WR I don't like that I don't
like that in fact I stopped writing
letters recommendation because there's a
couple of cases where I took an
exception to that because I've been with
them for six years some of them um and
but most of the time I didn't it was you
know if you pay me to mention I'm not
automat going to rate you you know a
glowing you know uh thing and um
actually failed the girl in French I was
a French lab instructor and I was dating
her and I failed
her because I just can't she was so bad
she was anyway the point is that this
poor guy uh had nothing to show for his
intelligence nothing he had nothing I I
I kept telling him every time he was
coming to me every single time he would
come to me he would tell he would tell
me he was he show me some really cool
thing and he just wanted he he was
learning all the time the guy was such a
natural autodidact but he also had a
problem that I share I have the same
problem he was easily bored so he would
like work on a thing and then he would
work on another thing and he'd work on
another thing and then he'd come to my
mentoring session and he didn't have any
questions or anything he just wanted to
sit there and talk about all the cool
stuff that he' be done because nobody
could even talk to the guy because he
was talking about things that were so
far above the heads of most adults even
and I would just sit here in awe of him
i' say yes teach me your ways I I'm I'm
here for you you know because you know
he just wanted somebody to talk to and
and I would I would you know reflect
back what I could to help him on his way
and every single time as his you know
Mentor I would say okay now how are you
going to share this with others he like
well I don't know and it was just like
his his brain just fried from the
question why would I care about sharing
it with anybody else I don't really need
to it's just fun I just like it I'm like
well you're you know you need to have
something you need to have something to
show for what you're doing so that you
can produce you know somebody else
can look at that and go damn that's cool
and not just me I mean I know you like
showing me but how are we going to show
other people so that we can help you you
know get the a really great you know
entrance into whatever or to get a job
or something I mean other people at his
age by the way had already had jobs we
had one uh uh yeah they already had jobs
we had people working for solar energy
companies they had 16year olds doing all
kinds of stuff uh in the tech realm and
you know coding C for a software company
um you know
because why because they they had
produced stuff they even silly stuff
that was in their GitHub and they could
talk about the stuff that they had
produced and they could get uh an
employer even at you know 16 they could
get them to hire them and very many of
them got really excellent jobs but this
one hyper intellig I mean intelligence
wise I don't like doing this but you
know his ability to comprehend very
complex uh ideas and to you know produce
very know quantitative mathematics in
his head was O over 9,000 the guy was
crazy but he could not get a job it was
one of these I know he can do the job
but can he get the job no he couldn't he
could never get a job you know why
because he had nothing to do to prepare
for that and his mom came to me and she
said you know um can you help me's we're
getting ready to get him into college
and everything and I said I have been
telling him for the last three years
that he needs to start producing
something of value so that you can Pro
and he's like cuz he didn't ever want to
focus on one project so I said okay how
about this how about you blog about your
discoveries how about you write notes
about that we're going to get on to that
whole topic but how about how about you
document just for yourself your personal
discoveries and your you know your your
learning experiments that you're doing
and and he's like why would I write that
down like just for your own sake you
mean you know I think you imagine
yourself you're like an old school
scientist right and you are learning new
things all the time and you're writing
your your stuff down and you just happen
to make it public you know and it didn't
have to be a zcast it could just be
notes right they just write your notes
down in the form of a blog when you come
to a point where you feel like you've
kind of put to bed this idea you can
write about it and then you can
demonstrate one that you know how to
communicate which you know that was his
Challenge and and two that you can
actually um communicate about the idea
to somebody else in a way that would
have value to them potentially so they
want to employ and then and then you put
a link to that blog or you you know you
refer to that information to your
journal or whatever you want to call it
your academic journal and and then you
refer to that in your in your thing and
then when I'm writing uh when I'm
writing a referral for you I'm saying he
has regularly you know devoted himself
to learning lab
experimentation uh and you know
exploring different concepts to to a
level and then documenting his
discoveries as he's gone and sharing it
with the public that's something that I
can really get behind as you know
somebody who wants to help other people
trust him as well as me because I mean a
lot of times he was telling me stuff and
I I I didn't have the ability to dive
into it and get to understand it or to
trust it better but if I had had sort of
a lay person's explanation of the
highest level and then be it was just
one approach to to a problem most people
don't have this problem uh who are
preparing to get jobs or to go to
college or something because they are
producing you know Silly software you
know they and by the way just because
it's we're going to talk about this
later but just because it's silly
doesn't mean it's bad right just because
it's like you know some game or
something like that th those things
demonstrate you know motivation and
passion and you know the the desire to
share it and everything th so those
things are very they work and potential
employers if they can see that you learn
how to do a thing even if it's a silly
game um they'll understand that you have
the capacity to be taught to learn
something else and the good employers
would never hire you just for a language
unless they're really in a bind they
would hire you for your ability to learn
and your ability to code and your
passion and those are the things that
they're looking for um that they're not
even really they're looking for mental
aptitude and intelligence but they're
mostly looking for a good work ethic and
proof that you can be trusted and the
ability to communicate and some of those
things are lacking and you you need to
be able to produce those things so
that's how employment happens uh that's
the story uh what happened to my friend
um he did get in he didn't get into the
colleges that he wanted to which is
really sad he he there was a couple of
colleges he ended up wanting to go to so
he he fell back to going to his um uh to
Colombia where you know his his family
was all all went to Colombia he didn't
really have to this is horrible to say
but he didn't have to prove himself as
much to get into Colombia as he did some
of these other schools he wanted to go
to because because his family had been
going to Columbia forever I think he's I
think somebody may have even taught
there and so yeah he got into Columbia
like that which is another we can talk
about why Iva League schools are a waste
of time and energy and money uh and
that's one of the reasons people get in
there and you get in there you work hard
and you get in there and somebody else
gets in there just because they knew
somebody or their their mom and dad went
there and now you're working with this
person and they're on the same team as
you both of you are contributing to your
grades and and I don't want to be around
those
people I mean I really like this guy a
lot he was really he was a real genius I
would never want to work with him and I
tried really really hard to for him to
help him understand he would it's going
to take a very unique uh work envir for
that particular person um because
because he lacked so many of the other
skills that are critical to an
employment um and and and building trust
was one of them he he had all of the raw
capacity to be uh you know a six-figure
employed you know first job kind of
person but he had none of the ability to
produce trust in the people that would
hire him to do stuff for them because he
hadn't focused on that because he didn't
feel like it was important and and I you
know you know when I when I left I hope
he's changed since then but when I when
I left him he never really got it he
never really saw how important it is to
focus on that relationship building and
building trust and producing proof that
you can do the job not just get the job
I'm not arguing that with you